SABIR KOTTEPARAMBIL MAITHEEN

Contact: +971 50 341 9265 Email: mgrsabir@gmail.com Address: Abudhabi, UAE



Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer

MEP Construction • Facilities Management • Operations & Maintenance • Project Development • Oil & Gas



Career Summary

A strategic and experienced Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer with more than 10 years of progressive experience and technical expertise in Installation, Inspection, Calibration, Testing, Commissioning, Maintenance and Troubleshooting of various machines, equipment and instruments in Power Plants and Oil & Gas projects to achieve high availability and maximum performance. Demonstrate leadership and strong results in Project Management, Operational Excellence, Electrical Engineering, Coordination of Instruments & Control Systems and Manpower Management.

Comprehensive knowledge of designing, developing and installing **new gas skids**, **electrical power cables**, **control valves and field instruments** as per required specifications while focusing on safety, reliability, quality and sustainability. Extensive project management experience including coordinating various electrical projects, preparing project documents, developing budgets, meeting client requirements, implementing project procedures, evaluating project performance and making sure the project is completed on time and within budget.



Career Objective

Seeking a challenging role as an Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer with specialization in Oil & Gas Projects, MEP Construction, Facilities Management, Operations and Maintenance where rich experience, exceptional project management skills and strong work ethic will be utilized towards achieving the organizational goals and objectives.



Career Snapshot

July 2021 - Present Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer @ GISCO UAE.

Sep 2020 - Feb 2021 Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer

Total Power Solutions Engineering LLC, Fujairah, UAE

Jan 2020 - Sep 2020 Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer

Albanna Engineering LLC, Dubai, UAE

Dec 2018 - Dec 2019 Industrial Engineer General

Eram Group, Abu Dhabi, UAE

Mar 2018 - Dec 2018 Electrical & Instrumentation Engineer

Metal Fab Middle East FZ LLC, Ras Al Khaima, UAE

May 2016 - Oct 2017 Control Room Instrumentation Engineer

Oman National Engineering & Investment Co. Ltd.

(ONEIC), Oman

Sep 2015 - Nov 2015 Quality Control Inspector

Al Najim Saudi International Co. Ltd. (NASICO),

Saudi Arabia

Jun 2011 - Aug 2015 Instrumentation Engineer

T3 Projects Private Limited, Kerala, India



Educational Attainment

Master of Technology in Chemical Process
Control Engineering

Calicut University, Kerala, India 2014

Bachelor of Technology in Electronics & Instrumentation Engineering

Mahatma Ghandi University, Kerala, India 2011



Personal Profile

Date of Birth: 4th March 1989

Nationality: Indian

Marital Status: Married

Languages: English, Hindi, Tamil,

Malayalam & Arabic

Driving License: Valid UAE D/L

Visa Status: Employment Visa

Passport No.: T3284243

References: Available Upon Request



Technical Skills

Ladder Diagram DOS
SCADA C, C++
PLC Aspen Plus

AirportP&IDSiteHTML

DCSJAVAPCS7HYSYSMATLABSIMULINK

Microsoft Office
 LATEX



Areas of Expertise

- Electrical Engineering
- ➤ Instruments and Control Systems
- Building Management Systems (BMS)
- Preventative Maintenance & Troubleshooting
- Testing & Commissioning
- ➤ Resource Allocation
- Estimation, Tendering & Proposal

- Building Automation System (BAS)
- Quality Control Analysis
- Project Management

Contact: +971 50 341 9265

- Project Monitoring & Evaluation
- Strategic Planning & Execution
- > Technical Awareness & Support
- Value Engineering

- Valve Inspection & Testing
- Client Relationship Management
- Electrical Drawings
- Instrument Data Sheet
- > Team Leadership/Management
- Power Plants & Systems
- Risk Analysis & Mitigation



Employment History



Total Power Solutions Engineering LLC (TPS) is a multi-faceted engineering company with expertise in trouble shooting, repair, maintenance, upgrade of plants & machineries for Marine, Heavy Industries and Offshore sector around the globe.



Sep 2020 - Present

ELECTRICAL & INSTRUMENTATION ENGINEER

Total Power Solutions Engineering LLC, Fujairah, UAE

Job Responsibilities:

- Playing an integral role in spearheading major projects in Fujairah Oil Tanker Terminals (FOTT) and Port of Fujairah (POF), Fujairah, UAE which include:
 - "Installation of Float & Tape Level Gauge in New Foam Tank in MM1 Area" of FOTT, near Gate No. 24
 - "Calibration of all Field Instruments in FOTT MM1, MM2, OTB9 & VLCC Area" in the yard of Port of Fujairah (POF), Fujairah, UAE
 - o "Building Civil, Mechanical & Electrical Rectification Works inside FOTT" in the Yard of Port of Fujairah, UAE
- Optimized and managed electrical and instrumentation activities throughout the project life cycle in accordance with the applicable health, safety, and environment standards. Expertise in PCS7 Automation Design & Installation systems.
- Ensured safety of workers and proper implementation of the projects based on the agreed timeline, budget, safety measurements and other relevant requirements.



Established in 1984, **Albanna Engineering** delivers a range of EPCM solutions involving the complete engineering spectrum of services being design, civil, mechanical, structural, electrical and instrumentation engineering.



Jan 2020 - Sep 2020

ELECTRICAL & INSTRUMENTATION ENGINEER

Albanna Engineering LLC, Dubai, UAE

Job Responsibilities:

- Contributed to the development, procurement, installation, testing and commissioning of electrical, control, instrumentation and power systems including New Gas Skid in EGA sites based on Al Taweelah (EMAL) and Jebel Ali (DUBAL).
- In-charge of the strategic planning and implementation of major projects in CPP, which include SEOT Phase II in Jebel Ali while maximizing the overall efficiency in monitoring progress of the work.
- Directed and trained a highly functional team by providing technical guidance and support in the installation, preventative maintenance, repair and troubleshooting of electrical systems and equipment.
- Served as the primary point of contact in maintaining open communication with sub-vendors to manage contractual terms and conditions throughout the bidding process.
- Communicated accurate engineering information across multiple teams and departments to facilitate successful completion of projects. Expertise in PCS7 Automation Systems.
- Expanded professional and technical knowledge of leading-edge developments in electrical and instrumentation engineering through participation in professional organizations, networking events, and reviewing latest publications.
- Proactively identified and resolved any challenge or issue while ensuring that all handled projects are completed on time, as per the specifications and within the budget.
- Monitored and evaluated performance measures for control and instrumentation systems to ensure maximum efficiency and full compliance.



Based in Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) region, Eram Group is a diversified conglomerate mainly operating in Oil & Gas, Power & Utilities, Travel, Food, Healthcare and Automotive sectors.



Dec 2018 - Dec 2019

INDUSTRIAL ENGINEER GENERAL

Eram Group, Abu Dhabi, UAE

Contact: +971 50 341 9265

Job Responsibilities:

- Involved in the design, procurement, installation, testing and commissioning of HV, MV & LV cable works in MTB project while evaluating overall processes and identify areas of improvement. Expertise in PCS7 Automation Systems.
- Coordinated closely with the Civil team in Abu Dhabi Airport Midfield Terminal Building Construction Project in implementing modification to the infrastructure projects while analyzing and mitigating potential risks.
- Demonstrated proven expertise in managing the cost estimation and tendering process to ensure that the required quantity, cost, and price of the resources are implemented to complete the project at specified cost in specified time.
- Successfully completed HV, MV and LV cable installation works including but not limited to container ships at Drydocks World Dubai Shipyard platform, the largest ship repair facility in the Middle East.

METALFAB

Metal Fab Middle East provides services that encompass design, engineering, procurement, fabrication, surface preparation and protection, installation, erection and commissioning.



Mar 2018 - Dec 2018

ELECTRICAL & INSTRUMENTATION ENGINEER

Metal Fab Middle East FZ LLC, Ras Al Khaima, UAE

Job Responsibilities:

- Acquired hands-on experience and strong expertise in the strategic planning and project implementation which include:
 - Chemical Injection Skids (Oxy Oman)
- o Flare Gas Recovery Unit (KNPC Kuwait)
- Instrument Air Compressor Skid (Rania) o Instrument Air Compressor Skid (PDO Oman)
- Accountable for designing, programming, simulating and testing various machinery and processes to ensure completion of day-to-day tasks or activities.
- Established and strengthened strategic partnerships and relationships with major clients and sub-vendors by providing sound advice in terms of commercial and technical matters.
- Maintained open communication with the Managing Director, Project Manager and customers by providing regular updates about the critical aspects and progress of the project to take action and address project issues and risks.
- Involved in the preparation and development of detailed electrical drawings and instrument data sheets in line with the client's requirements and specifications.
- Offered insightful and strategic inputs to Structural & Piping Department by understanding their specific requirements and formulating the design of skids accordingly.
- Exhibited strong leadership and skills in Technical Bid Evaluation of Quote and Bill of Materials (BOM) Preparation for instrumentation items.
- Conducted loop testing for pressure transmitters, gear flow meters, level transmitters, etc on skids to ensure that the system works without malfunctions and correct the deficiencies before commissioning.

CONTROL ROOM INSTRUMENTATION ENGINEER

May 2016 - Oct 2017

Email: mgrsabir@gmail.com

Oman National Engineering & Investment Co. Ltd. (ONEIC), Oman

QUALITY CONTROL INSPECTOR

Sep 2015 - Nov 2015

Al Najim Saudi International Co. Ltd. (NASICO), Saudi Arabia

INSTRUMENTATION ENGINEER

T3 Projects Private Limited, Kerala, India

Jun 2011 - Aug 2015

Other Qualifications

- Published M. Tech. Thesis in "International Conference on Advances in Chemical Engineering and Technology, ICACE TKMCE '14 (119-124)" based on the topic "Mathematical Model for Algae Production in a Raceway Reactor" via Elsevier Publications Ltd. in 2014.
- Qualified Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (G.A.T.E.) 2012 Exam with a valid score of 408 out of 1000.
- Attended 3-month Skill Development Course in "Instrumentation Maintenance & Control Systems" at F.A.C.T. Training Center at Udyogamandal, Ernakulam District, Kerala, India.
- Attended BASIC H2S TRAINING (OPITO APPROVED) COURSE CODE 9014 for working in ADNOC Offshore Platform.
- Attended ADNOC OFFSHORE HSE INDUCTION for working in ADNOC Offshore Platform.